Guide to the Charles Wishaw Clubbe papers, 1840-1878 MS 307
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Charles Wishaw Clubbe papers
1840-1878
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Clubbe, Charles Wishaw
MS 307
0.25 Linear Feet (4 folders)
Most of this collection, which dates from 1840 to 1878, is comprised of correspondence from British politician and statesman Benjamin Disraeli to Rev. Clubbe, who occupied the position of vicar at the living of Hughenden near High Wycombe in Buckinghamshire, from approximately 1851 to 1868.
Biographical Note
Charles Wishaw Clubbe (1823-1886) occupied the position of vicar at the living of Hughenden near High Wycombe in Buckinghamshire, from approximately 1851 to 1868. Hughenden Manor had been purchased by Benjamin Disraeli (1804 to 1881), one of Great Britain's outstanding politicians and statesmen of the nineteenth century, in September 1848. Clubbe's appointment was made at the express wish of Mr. Disraeli.
Scope and Contents
Most of this collection, which dates from 1840 to 1878, is comprised of correspondence from Benjamin Disraeli to Rev. Clubbe. However, in addition, there are several letters from Mary Anne Disraeli to Clubbe, along with notes from Disraeli's secretaries to Clubbe, as well as family correspondence.
N.B. The researcher's attention is drawn to the usage of the term 'Lady Beaconsfield' in several letters by Mary Anne Disraeli before 1876, which is the date when Benjamin Disraeli received his peerage. This inconsistency remains unsolved.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored onsite at the Woodson Research Center.
Acquisition Information
Purchased 1953-55 from Myers & Co., through the Friends of Fondren Library.
Related Archival Materials note
See published volumes of the correspondence of Disraeli, Benjamin, Earl of Beaconsfield, 1804-1881.
Index Terms
Subjects
Religion; Prime ministers -- Correspondence; Churches
Document Types
invitations; corrrespondence; marriage licenses
Places
Great Britain
Subjects (Persons)
Disraeli, Benjamin
Subjects (Corporations)
Church of England
- Series I: Correspondence, 1842-1860
  - Grace Barbee to Mrs. W. Barbee, January 7, 1840; Letter 1: (Folder 1)
  - John Hays to C. W. Clubbe. Giving Clubbe the news of the results of the exams from Cambridge., December 17, 1842; Letter 2: (Folder 1)
  - John Hays to C. W. Clubbe (also includes note from C. W. Clubbe's brother). Letter saying the results from Cambridge had been changed, and that Clubbe had been dropped two places in the standings. Also attached is a note from Clubbe's brother., December 19, 1842; Letter 3: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe, June 25, 1847; Letter 4: (Folder 1)
  - C. W. Clubbe to Mrs. C. W. Clubbe. Domestic affairs - recounting his actions in her absence., February 18, 1852; Letter 5: (Folder 1)
  - C. W. Clubbe to Mrs. C. W. Clubbe. Domestic affairs in wife's absence., February 19, 1852; Letter 6: (Folder 1)
  - C. W. Clubbe to Mrs. C. W. Clubbe. Domestic affairs in wife's absence., February 23, 1852; Letter 7: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Relating to an enclosure which made Clubbe au fait with some things he should know., August 16, 1852; Letter 8: (Folder 1)
  - Margaret Warren to "Emily". Recipient is probably Clubbe's wife., December 13, 1853; Letter 9: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Relating to a book in the post for the Clubbes., May 5, 1854; Letter 10: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Asking Clubbe to distribute £5 worth of coal for him in Hughenden., February 11, 1855; Letter 11: (Folder 1)
  - Mary Anne Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe, March 28, 1859; Letter 12: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Asking Clubbe to dinner to meet the Bishop., November 7, 1860; Letter 13: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Asking for a subscription list., January 28, 1862; Letter 14: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Trying to arrange a mutually convenient meeting date., September 30, 1862; Letter 15: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Relating to some business transacted by Clubbe on Disraeli's behalf., October 15, 1862; Letter 16: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Relating the conduct of the Disraeli estate at Hughenden., January 1, 1863; Letter 17: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Reporting the illness of his brother., January 27, 1863; Letter 18: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe, September 17, 1863; Letter 19: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Relating to a proposed burial at Hughenden., November 12, 1863; Letter 20: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Relating to a new vault and a burial to take place at Hughenden., November 14, 1863; Letter 21: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. A note of thanks., November 19, 1863; Letter 22: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Asking if the vault at Hughenden has been closed and asking Clubbe to take care of it if it hasn't., November 21, 1863; Letter 23: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Relating to business affairs at Hughenden., February 15, 1864; Letter 24: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Relating to Disraeli's business affairs in London and Hughenden., August 3, 1864; Letter 25: (Folder 1)
  - Mary Anne Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe, April 29, 1865; Letter 26: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe, July 5, 1865; Letter 27: (Folder 1)
  - C. W. Clubbe to Secretary of Education Department. Relating to Hughenden's school fences and other like matters., October 27, 1865; Letter 28: (Folder 1)
  - C. W. Clubbe to Secretary of Education Department. A reply to some prior correspondence enclosing some plans and an agreement upon which some land has been let., November 24, 1865; Letter 29: (Folder 1)
  - Acknowledgement of receipt of letter from C. W. Clubbe on, November 24, November 29, 1865; Item 30: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Asking for the amount of a contribution., December 20, 1865; Letter 31: (Folder 1)
  - C. W. Clubbe to Secretary of Education Department. A request for information on the prospective cost of building a house., December 21, 1865; Letter 32: (Folder 1)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Asking if some of his papers are among Rev. Clubbe's., January 9, 1866; Letter 33: (Folder 1)
  - Emily M. Clubbe to Grandmother (Mrs. C. W. Clubbe?). The relatioship here is probably that of Grandaughter to Grandmother. The letter relates to passing domestic events., August 23, 1866; Letter 34: (Folder 1)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1867-1878
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Informing him of the improvement in his wife's condition., March 18, 1867; Letter 1: (Folder 2)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe, November 20, 1867; Letter 2: (Folder 2)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. The doctors will not let Mrs Disraeli go to Hughenden though she continues to improve., December 11, 1867; Letter 3: (Folder 2)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Referring to business at Hughenden., April 15, 1868; Letter 4: (Folder 2)
  - Montagu Corry to C. W. Clubbe. Asking Clubbe to go to London to discuss with Disraeli the possibilities of his accepting a living in West Ham., May 4, 1868; Letter 5: (Folder 2)
  - Abel J. Ram to C. W. Clubbe. From West Ham giving Mr. Clubbe the details of the out-going finances of the West Ham living., May 12, 1868; Letter 6: (Folder 2)
  - Montagu Corry to C. W. Clubbe. Note thanking him (Clubbe) for his letter and reply concerning the West Ham living., May 14, 1868; Letter 7: (Folder 2)
  - Montagu Corry to C. W. Clubbe. Letter to say that Disraeli is to suggest to the Queen the living in Gigglethorpe, Yorkshire for Mr. Clubbe., October 1, 1868; Letter 8: (Folder 2)
  - Mary Anne Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe, October 4, 1868; Letter 9: (Folder 2)
  - Sir Charles Fremantle to C. W. Clubbe, November 7, 1868; Letter 10: (Folder 2)
  - Mary Anne Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe, December 4, 1868; Letter 11: (Folder 2)
  - Lady Beaconsfield (Mary Anne Disraeli) to C. W. Clubbe, February 26, 1869; Letter 12: (Folder 2)
  - Lady Beaconsfield (Mary Anne Disraeli) to C. W. Clubbe, June 15, 1869; Letter 13: (Folder 2)
  - Lady Beaconsfield (Mary Anne Disraeli) to C. W. Clubbe, August 12, 1870; Letter 14: (Folder 2)
  - Lady Beaconsfield (Mary Anne Disraeli) to C. W. Clubbe, April 16, 1871; Letter 15: (Folder 2)
  - Lady Beaconsfield (Mary Anne Disraeli) to C. W. Clubbe, June 20, 1871; Letter 16: (Folder 2)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to Mrs. C. W. Clubbe. Asking to borrow Mrs Clubbe's father's journal of the 1830's., August 3, 1871; Letter 17: (Folder 2)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to Mrs. C. W. Clubbe. Re-affirming that the manuscript journal of the late Mr Clubbe (?) was not at Grosvenor Place., October 9, 1871; Letter 18: (Folder 2)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to Mrs. C. W. Clubbe. A letter relating the memoir., October 29, 1871; Letter 19: (Folder 2)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to Mrs. C. W. Clubbe. Informing her that the manuscript journal had been found., November 12, 1871; Letter 20: (Folder 2)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to C. W. Clubbe. Informing them that Lady Beaconsfield had not been well, and that they intend to reach Hughenden at some point., September 18, 1872; Letter 21: (Folder 2)
  - Benjamin Disraeli to Mrs. C. W. Clubbe, October 22, 1872; Letter 22: (Folder 2)
  - Charles Campbell? to C. W. Clubbe. Informing Mr. Clubbe that he has been given two seats in the 'Gallery'., June 4, 1874; Letter 23: (Folder 2)
  - Montagu Corry to C. W. Clubbe. Expressing his condolences at the loss of Mrs Clubbe's mother; refers to the enjoyable, and, hopefully therapeutic, days spent at Hughenden by Mrs. Disraeli and himself., January 9, 1878; Letter 24: (Folder 2)
- Series III: Correspondence, undated
  - Margaret Barbee to C. W. Clubbe, n.d. (July 12 ?); Letter 1: (Folder 3)
  - Emily Barbee to C. W. Clubbe, n.d. (Thursday); Letter 2: (Folder 3)
  - C. W. Clubbe to Mrs. C. W. Clubbe, n.d. (Wednesday); Letter 3: (Folder 3)
  - C. W. Clubbe's Mother to C. W. Clubbe, n.d. (July 6 ?); Letter 4: (Folder 3)
  - unknown to C. W. Clubbe, n.d.; Letter 5: (Folder 3)
  - Four Envelopes addressed to C. W. Clubbe, n.d.; Item 6: (Folder 3)
- Series IV: Invitations and Marriage License, 1843-1869
  - Invitation to royal visit of University of Cambridge, October, 1843; Item 1: (Folder 4)
  - Marriage License for Mr. and Mrs. C. W. Clubbe, July 26, 1850; Item 2: (Folder 4)
  - Invitation to consecration of the Chapel of St. Johns College, Cambridge, May 12, 1869; Item 3: (Folder 4)